A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2000-2006
Library of Virginia
- Series VI. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006., Extent: 118 folders. (Folder 1-4)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Geographic Information System (GIS), 2005. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Green Bean Insurance, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- ID - Animal Identification, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Jamestown / Yorktown (400th Anniversary), 2005. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Japan - Mizkan Sanmi Co. / Toyota Tsusho Corp., 2005. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Land Use, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Media Files, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Migrant Seasonal Farm Workers, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Nitamin Steady-Delivery Nitrogen Fertilizer Technology, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Nonpoint Source Nutrient Management, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 42 (1 of 2))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Nonpoint Source Nutrient Management, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 43 (2 of 2))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Northampton County Chamber of Commerce - Tourism Strategy for Virginia's Eastern Shore, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals (PETA), 2005. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Perdue Farms, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Performance-Based Budgeting, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Pilgrim's Pride Corporation, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Poultry, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Poultry - Agricultural Market Development, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Rail Enhancement Fund, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Resource Conservation and Development Councils, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Revenue Data, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Sloan Foundation / Virginia Polytechnic Institute Forest Industries Center, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Spay Virginia, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- State Fair of Virginia, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Statewide Agencies Radio System (STARS), 2005. (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Strategic Plan - Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Sustainable Future Summit, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Tobacco, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Tyson Foods, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Agricultural Council, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Agriculture and Nature Center - Eugenia L. Nelson, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 4 (1 of 2))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Agriculture and Nature Center - Eugenia L. Nelson, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 5 (2 of 2))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Commonwealth University Class, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Executive Institute (VEI), 2005. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Northern Neck Farm Museum, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia State University, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Stream Alliance, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Wineries Association, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Works, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- "Virginia's Finest" Trademark Program, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Water Quality, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Web Page, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Web Page Standard, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, June - December 2004. (Box 3, Folder 17 (1 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, January - June 2004. (Box 3, Folder 18 (2 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, October - December 2003. (Box 3, Folder 19 (3 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, June - September 2003. (Box 3, Folder 20 (4 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, March - May 2003. (Box 3, Folder 21 (5 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, November 2002 - February 2003. (Box 3, Folder 22 (6 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, August 2002 - October 2002. (Box 3, Folder 23 (7 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, March - July 2002. (Box 3, Folder 24 (8 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, November 2001 - March 2002. (Box 3, Folder 25 (9 of 9))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agricultural Enterprise Zone Act, House Bill 2805, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agriculture and Forestry Action Team, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Doubling Agriculture Receipts, 2001-2003. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Poultry Issues, 2002-2004. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Speech - Business Leadership Breakfast, July 21, 2005, 2004-2005. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Agribusiness Council, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Farm Bureau, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 33 (1 of 2))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 34 (2 of 2))
  - Forestry, Department of -- General Correspondence, January - August 2005. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Forestry, Department of -- General Correspondence, October 2003 - December 2004. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Forestry, Department of -- General Correspondence, February 2002 - July 2003. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Budget, 2002-2003. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Camp Roosevelt - Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) Legacy Foundation, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Community Tree Planting, 2000-2006. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Forest Fires, 2002. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Forest Legacy - Sandy Point, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Forestry - Summit - Goals, 2004-2005. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Forestry Tours, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Lex Logging and Construction Inc., 2005. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Reforestation of Timberlands, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Research - Timber Industry, Forest Management Public Opinion Research, and Marketal Survey on Public Opinions Towards Forestry Issues for Virginia Forestry and Forest Products Council, 1993-2003, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 12 (1 of 3))
  - Forestry, Department of -- Research - Timber Industry, Forest Management Public Opinion Research, and Marketal Survey on Public Opinions Towards Forestry Issues for Virginia Forestry and Forest Products Council, 1993-2003, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 13 (2 of 3))
  - Forestry, Department of -- Research - Timber Industry, Forest Management Public Opinion Research, and Marketal Survey on Public Opinions Towards Forestry Issues for Virginia Forestry and Forest Products Council, 1993-2003, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 14 (3 of 3))
  - Forestry, Department of -- Silvicultural Water Quality Program, 2004-2005. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Forestry, Department of -- State of the Forrest, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Series VII: Hiring Requests, 2002-2005., Extent: 8 folders. (Folder 4)
  This series contains hiring requests submitted by the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services as well as the Department of Forestry to their designated Cabinet Secretary. The requests document instances of agencies seeking authorization to fill a vacant position. Each request contains the position title, the position pay scale, a narrative explanation of why the position needs to be filled, alternatives to filling the position with a paid employee, and the impact the agency may expect if the position goes unfilled. The requests bear either the approval or disapproval of either Secretary of Commerce and Trade Michael J. Schewel or Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry Robert Bloxom. Control of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the Department of Forestry was transferred from Michael J. Schewel, the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, to Robert S. Bloxom after his appointment to the position of Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry in December 2004. Some requests feature handwritten notes from Michael J. Schewel and Robert S. Bloxom. The requests are organized first by agency and are in chronological order.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2004. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2003. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2002. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2004. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2003. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Forestry, Department of -- Agency Hiring Requests, 2002. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series VIII: Recognition Requests,, 2002-2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 4)
  This series contains recognition requests sent to the office of Governor Mark R. Warner by the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services. Recognition requests are forms that petition for the official recognition of a notable date, person, event, or object through the issuance of a certificate or greeting from the governor. Requests may also petition for the designation of a particular date or span of time in honor of whatever person, object, or concept is being recognized. Forms of recognition may include but are not limited to certificates of recognition, birthday greetings, and anniversary announcements.
  The recognition requests in this series are exclusively for certificates of recognition and petition the Governor's office for the designation of certain days, weeks, and months as periods of time to honor different aspects of agriculture. Examples include requests to designate December 2005 as Virginia Christmas Tree Month, October 2005 as Virginia Pumpkin Month as well as Virginia Apple Month, the week of August 7, 2005 as Virginia Farmers Market Week, and September 2002 as the 125th anniversary of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services. Included with each request is a draft of the pertinent information to be included in the desired certificate. The drafts contain the reasons why each object, concept, or entity is worthy of recognition and explain their significance to the Commonwealth. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Recognition Requests, 2002-2005. (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Series IX: Reports and Supporting Documentation - Prospects and Development, 2001-2005., Extent: 4 folders. (Folder 4)
  This series contains drafts and completed reports and studies created by the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, and the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services. The reports were submitted to either the appropriate Secretariat (Commerce and Trade or Agriculture and Forestry), or the Governor, special committees, or the Virginia General Assembly. This series contains reports from the Secretary of Commerce and Trade because control of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services passed from the Office of Secretary of Commerce and Trade to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry following the Office's creation and the appointment of Bloxom in late 2004. Reports and studies represented in this series include annual agency activity reports and topical reports concerning issues such as the purchase of land development rights from land owners, the Virginia equine industry, agency budgets, agricultural development problems, and agency performance goals among other topics. As many of these reports are drafts, this series may be of interest to researchers who desire to see changes between the draft report and the report in its final form. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Reports and Supporting Documentation, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Reports and Supporting Documentation, 2004. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Reports and Supporting Documentation, 2003. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Reports and Supporting Documentation, 2001-2002. (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Series X: Regulation Reviews and Supporting Documentation, 2002., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 4)
  This series contains proposed agricultural regulations submitted to Secretary of Commerce and Trade Michael J. Schewel and the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services for comment. Regulatory topics included in this series include the storage of milk, the removal of three species from the List of Threatened and Endangered Plant and Insect Species, the development and review process for regulations proposed by state agencies, and pesticide regulations. Prior to the creation of the Secretariat of Agriculture and Forestry, the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the Department of Forestry reported to the Secretary of Commerce and Trade. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Regulation Reviews and Supporting Documentation, 2002. (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Series XI: Secretary's Website, 2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 4)
  This series contains several different types of records pertaining to the creation of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry's website. Included in this series are draft versions of individual website pages, content notes, biographical information about the Secretary and Deputy Secretary, and email regarding the website's creation. The draft website pages included in this series range from strictly informational to nearly complete formats and include handwritten annotations discussing potential changes in the draft's informational content and artistic design. Most of the documents in this series are handwritten drafts of agency mission statements and synopses of agency projects written for the viewing public. The email in this series discuss what agency facts and services will be placed on the website and how the website will be structured. Two items of particular interest in this series are highly detailed biographical sketches of Secretary Robert S. Bloxom and Deputy Secretary William P. Dickinson, Jr. Further information regarding the creation of the Secretary's website can be found in box 3, folders 14 and 15 of Series VI: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006.
  - Secretary's Website Records, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Series XII: Special Project Files, 2002-2003., Extent: 6 folders. (Folder 5-6)
  This series contains the files of what the Secretary of Commerce and Trade classified as special projects. The files in this series were created before the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services was transferred from the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade to the Office of the Secretary and Agriculture and Forestry after December 2004. Major topics represented in this series and of interest to researchers include avian influenza and drought. The avian influenza epidemic file documents the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services' response to the 2002 outbreak of avian influenza (commonly referred to as "avian flu" or "bird flu") that began on a turkey farm in Virginia's Shenandoah Valley and the department's efforts to provide guidance and relief to affected poultry farms and farmers. Documents in the avian influenza epidemic file include statistical sheets detailing the number of afflicted birds and their values, correspondence from poultry flock owners requesting assistance in dealing with the outbreak and removing dead flocks, and plans concerning the possibility of indemnity payoffs to poultry growers who experienced losses.
  The drought disaster designations files document Virginia's response to instances of significant drought in 2002 and early 2003. Documents include, among other things, letters from county officials and residents to the office of Governor Mark R. Warner and from Governor Warner to the U.S. Department of Agriculture asking for declarations of drought disasters in affected Virginia counties. Damage assessment reports from the U.S. Department of Agriculture are also included, and were used to determine a particular area's worthiness while deciding if the area should be declared a disaster area. The Virginia Drought Task Force file documents a Commonwealth effort to draft a comprehensive plan for drought assessment and response. The creation of the task force was brought about by Governor Warner's Executive Order # 39, the Virginia Water Supply Initiative. Documents in the file include the taskforce's final plan, task force status reports, correspondence from Governor Mark R. Warner and others, presentation materials, and articles about drought among other things. Further information regarding drought can be found among the correspondence ain Series V: Constituent Correspondence, 2004-2005, and in Series VI: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006, box 2, folders 20-21. This series is arranged alphabetically by topic. This series is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of --Avian Influenza Epidemic, 2002. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of --Drought Disaster Designations, September 2002 - April 2003. (Box 5, Folder 2 (1 of 4))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of --Drought Disaster Designations, August -September 2002. (Box 5, Folder 3 (2 of 4))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of --Drought Disaster Designations, June - August 2002. (Box 5, Folder 4 (3 of 4))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of --Drought Disaster Designations, February - June 2002. (Box 5, Folder 5 (4 of 4))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of; and Forestry, Department of -- Virginia Drought Task Force, June 2002 - March 2003. (Box 5, Folder 6 (1 of 2))
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of; and Forestry, Department of -- Virginia Drought Task Force, March 2002- May 2002. (Box 6, Folder 1 (2 of 2))
- Series XIII: Travel Authorizations, 2002., Extent: 4 folders. (Folder 6)
  This series contains domestic and foreign travel authorization requests submitted by the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services to either the Secretary of Commerce and Trade or the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, depending on the date of the request. The Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services was removed from the control of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade and placed under the control of the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry following Robert S. Bloxom's appointment as Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry in December of 2004. The travel requests are authored by Commissioner J. Carlton Courter, III, Commissioner of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and were written on behalf of agency employees the department desired to send to conferences, tradeshows, or fact-finding trips.
  Each request includes a cover sheet detailing the rationale behind the proposed trip. Many requests include conference schedules, literature, and travel accommodation information. The requests themselves are standard forms that document information regarding the employee going on the trip, the length of the trip, the total cost, the justification for the trip, and any justifications for exceeding the allowance the agency will pay. Researchers may find this series particularly useful for examining both the outreach efforts and the day to day business of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services as each authorization includes a justification stating why the trip supports the business of the department. This series is arranged by the type of travel, foreign or domestic, and then chronologically.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Travel Authorizations, 2002-2005. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Travel Authorizations - Abroad, 2005. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Travel Authorizations - Abroad, 2004. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Travel Authorizations - Abroad, 2002-2003. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series XIV: Virginia Taskforce for Business Development in the Near East, 2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 6)